What if you can see what's actually working on YouTube right now before everybody else,
backed by data?
One of the largest studies of 50,000 YouTube channels was conducted and it actually revealed 12
new shifts that are driving YouTube growth right now.
This is an opinion.
They actually spent $10,000 on this study and your cost is $0.00.
I've got this broken down into the 12 insights based on questions.
And this is one of the biggest questions that comes in all the time, right?
What is the best video length on YouTube right now?
Well, there's actually an answer based off real data.
So check this out.
The ideal video length, if your videos are going to be under an hour,
is between 16 and 26 minutes.
The actual range in the study is for videos under an hour.
The sweet spot is 15 to 25 minutes for your videos.
And they revealed that the danger.
zone is 30 to 60 minutes. Now, how does this data show up? Well, there's a lot of information on the
page here, but right there you can see the danger zone. Shout out to Top Gun 1 with Tom Cruise. And there's
kind of a dip if your videos are in between 30 minutes to one hour. And what's fascinating, though,
is if we get into longer videos, like 150 minutes to 180 minutes long, then they really start to
fascinating. And that's because longer videos means more watch time, which means stronger
recommendations. So here's the big insight. How long should your videos be? Well, longer videos
that are over an hour tend to perform better on average. But if your videos are going to be
under an hour, the sweet spot is 15 to 25 minutes. Now, this is probably the best YouTube
tips video on the internet because this isn't just some like regurgitated info. This is some new
strategists from one of 10.com. That's where this study came from. They sourced 300,000 viral
videos, actual outliers, 62.6 billion views from 52,000 different channels, and they spent
$10,000 on this study. And these are some of the biggest insights. Here's the second one of 12.
Number two, does the best video length depend on your niche? Well, fascinating. Now, there's a lot of
But for example, this channel, think media, is a tech channel.
And the ideal video length is 28 minutes.
And the way they're studying that is, again,
you're getting more views, median views, based on the length of the video.
And it's a big range.
But if you're doing gaming or entertainment or sports, 15 to 30 minutes,
finance, business, or tech, 25 to 40 minutes.
I will link to the study in the description so you can look into it for yourself
the video and zoom in. But here's the thing. Most creators ask, how long should my video be?
Here's the better question. How long does my viewer expect the video to be? Because different
niches, the expectation of the audience is going to determine really your ideal video length.
And so the answer on video length is there is really no one size fits all. You want to be thinking
Niche's consistently support longer form content, food, DIY tutorial videos, kind of peak
with shorter to mid-length videos.
Now, number three is how long should your titles be?
This is where things get interesting.
And actually, towards the end of the video, I'm going to be breaking down the four things
you need to consider for coming up with the personalized strategy for you.
But here is the interesting things when it comes to how long should your YouTube
be? Well, here's the sweet spot. Five, six, seven, or eight words before things really start going
downhill. That's not a lot of words. So the shorter, the title, the better. Now, I was looking
up some of the videos on our Think Media podcast channel. By the way, if you want a good weekly YouTube
podcast, check out the Think Media podcast. And this video crushed, and it has a total of six
And it really outperformed a lot of our other videos.
There's a lot of other things going on there as well.
How about this one?
This one's eight words.
The future of YouTube do this before 2026.
Now, this is interesting.
This is a podcast interview, longer form.
I mean, an hour and 30 minutes, but check out the title,
genius personal branding tips with the guest interview, the person I'm interviewing.
So that is a total of seven words if you count the W with the slash.
get nearly 60% more views.
30 characters.
That's short.
So shorter titles are better than longer titles.
In fact, if you dig even deeper,
you can see here that the view count drops,
that blue line in the middle,
as the title gets longer.
And then also right here where the red arrow is pointing,
that's 70 characters, which is also important to know.
This is where YouTube begins.
to cut the title off on certain displays.
You understand that, right?
Like some, even if you have a really long title,
it gets like a dot, dot, dot.
It gets cut off depending on where the viewer is engaging with the video.
So really shorter titles are better.
However, there's kind of an exception here,
and that's education versus entertainment.
So what we're looking out here is that entertainment videos are the red line.
Five words, six words is way outperforming.
And then the line starts to drop pretty significantly, the red line,
as you add more words to your title.
If you notice on education, it's really not that dramatic.
I would still prefer to get more views on the left side, right?
But it's more of like a flat line.
So title length matters far more for entertainment videos than it does for education videos.
Remember, entertainment content is clicked
on impulse. So it creates, you know, you want to trigger curiosity, trigger emotion,
you want to win attention. Here's the big takeaway. Shorter titles win. And educational videos can be
a little longer, but still, shorter is still safer if you can condense your thoughts in the title.
Keep it simple, clear, fast to understand. And titles around 30 characters get way more clicks
than long ones. Number five, should I put my face in the thumbnail?
This is fascinating.
What they discovered in this report is that there's actually minimal difference in performance.
So what you see in the education on the left, entertainment on the right,
and education, if you have a face, it actually does a little bit better than not having a face.
And on entertainment, no face does better.
Okay, so no face does better in entertainment.
No face does a little bit weaker in education.
What's the big takeaway?
is that it's actually pretty close.
However, this shocked me.
If you dive into this, I know this is small.
You might need to zoom in on your mobile phone.
But let's just look at business content.
So business content that has a face
does not as well as no face in business content.
Now, here's a couple of disclaimers, right?
You have to start thinking about there's faceless channels.
Maybe they're talking about repurposing content, other people's content.
And people are just clicking on the topic itself,
and they want to learn something.
versus they're clicking on your face because you have some level of awareness as a personal brand.
You should consider those things.
But let's dive a little bit deeper.
If you look at lifestyle and vlog, of course, having a face outperforms, not having a face.
Probably because they know you.
However, lifestyle and vlog is also probably because they can relate to you.
So maybe if you want to reach new people with your vlog, you know, people watch people of all kinds
of different shapes and sizes.
But like if I'm a particular millennial mom that's blonde with five kids,
shopping at Costco.
I might follow other creators that I can kind of relate with.
So seeing who you're following matters in lifestyle and vlogging,
whereas, you know, even in tech down here, still having a face outperforms,
not having a face, but it's pretty close.
Now, this is even crazier.
Depending on how many faces, no face outperformed one face.
But if you've got two, three, or four faces, it jumped up even higher.
So that's interesting and why the one of 10 who did this study.
And again, I'll link to the Twitter of it.
And you can also actually download the full thing in the link of the bio of the account.
You know, they revealed that if there's multiple faces, it could be there's a moment happening,
a reaction of conflict maybe, or multiple people in the conversation.
It's going to be interesting.
There's something happening there.
And again, this is based on real data and not just somebody's opinion.
So should you have?
a face in your thumbnail. Well, it's going to depend on your niche, but overall, there's minimal
difference in performance. If you are a finance creator, you're doing business or education,
a face in general can signify trust, like I'm going to learn from a person and it's not just some
like chat cheapy-t AI script. Whereas if it's gaming, it's maybe, you know, Donkey Kong in Mario
Cart World, and that's like the hero, speed run. You're actually seeing the game, you're seeing the character.
or movie reaction. Maybe it's the, you know, the movie trailer of some kind.
And so what's the star? And you learn that two faces can outperform one face in a thumbnail.
Number six, should I add text to my thumbnail?
These should rock you. Let me know if you're surprised and hit the like button if you like content
like this.
Median views by text versus no text. No text radically outperformed thumbnails with text
in them. In fact, thumbnails with text get 19% fewer views on average. Wow. So you should try an attempt
to publish thumbnails with no text in them. Now look at this. You can see this strong
amount of meeting views hold strong. If you do include text, it is only up to 7% of the thumbnail.
Now let me put that in perspective. That's not a lot of the thumbnail. That is what 7% is. The little
box of an entire YouTube thumbnail.
Basically nothing.
So the big takeaway was if you can keep text out of your thumbnail, views go up,
click through rate goes up.
You know, on Think Media here, we do a lot of tech content,
and we have been always attempting to have no text in the thumbnail.
Great example, best webcams for every budget, no text.
Here is a good example of just one word.
That looks like about 7%.
It's kind of almost perfect to what it just said.
That's like 10% and then a little arrow pointing to it.
So like a simple emotion, something about, you know, whatever.
And a lot of times, again, we're striving to go no text.
Let the title do the heavy lifting.
You can see some stacked principles here.
This can in our six video, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, eight words.
So trying to keep your title short, punchy, and still clear.
But when necessary, remember in education, you can certainly go longer with the title
because there's a different.
Education viewers have intent to learn usually where entertainment viewers are really driven
off emotion. You're trying to get the click-through rate, get suggested in browse features.
And here's a great thumbnail that does the storytelling. I think that's what we're after.
There's no text in the thumbnail title, I tested 36 wireless microphones. Here are the best in a 14x
outlier here on our Think Media channel. So the question of should you include text in your thumbnail,
usually no. Show the idea. Don't label.
the idea. If you do use text, keep it under 10 characters, not words, 10 characters, and make it
tiny or keep it really minimal and bottom line, let the image do the talking. Number seven, how bright
should your thumbnails be? Your thumbnails should be bright, is the answer. The brighter of the thumbnail,
the better. And they did a bunch of ninja stuff based off of gray scale zero and measuring the
Natural brightness, 99 to like 100 is good, but a little bit brighter.
Like if you go into Canva or Photoshop, right, and a little bit brighter than even 100%
is where the higher performance was when it came to how bright should your thumbnails be.
Bottom line, brighter equals better, darker thumbnails get skipped.
You want to pop in the feed.
They're easier to see.
They get more clicks.
Number eight, what thumbnail colors work best?
This is a gangster report.
Are you enjoying this?
Ultimately, cyan, green, and yellow, orange performed the best you see in the middle there.
Now, quick caveat for this whole report is, you know, I think you could overanalyze some of these things
because, of course, I want to get the median views of 63,000 or 62,000.
But, you know, I'll still take 47,000 over here with like a white background or something.
So, you know, be realistic.
Virality is not accidental.
Like, these things do matter.
So understanding that these colors win, cyan, green, yellow, orange,
because they pop against YouTube's most neutral feed, mostly neutral feed,
they signal energy and clarity without visual fatigue.
I was surprised that red performed so poorly because some marketers, like, use red,
like it's really going to get attention.
Like, that'll shock people.
But maybe there's resistance to that.
You know, let me know your thoughts about these,
insights. And when you think about where YouTube is consumed, are people in dark mode?
Are they in white mode on their device? You want to preserve contrast even after YouTube's compression.
So the bottom line for what colors win most often in thumbnails, green, cyan, yellow, orange.
Now, number nine is do numbers help in your title? Should you put a number in your title?
Well, videos with numbers get 11% fewer views.
on average. Okay. So if a title has numbers, the median views across the niches and the
videos they studied was around 42,000 with no numbers that went up to, to 48,000 views. So out of the
study, 35% of the videos in the study included numbers in the titles. So three out of ten videos that
they studied had numbers in the title. But what it revealed was that if you can get the number
out of the title, you could get your views to go up.
And so why is that?
Well, numbers signify lists, explainers, tutorials, but they ultimately, they clarify structure,
but what people click on YouTube videos for is emotion.
And I think you could apply this in education as well.
A number is like, oh, I got to actually learn some things.
Now, you're watching this video because you want to learn some things,
but, you know, usually want to click because of the emotion and then you get into the things
you're going to learn.
Like, it's okay to have a list in your video.
So if you can package the video without a number,
It's interesting. Then don't include numbers in your titles. People click for a motion,
not structure. Numbers can still work, but they're not a cheat code. And by the way, these rules are
meant to be broken because, of course, you know, if I tested 36 mics, that's part of the story.
You know, if you click on the fact I visited 13 states. So take this information with a grain of salt,
but also understand that the knowledge of this video, I'd probably even rewatch this video and save it,
But this is real stuff. Number 10, what emotions get the most clicks?
Hmm. So across their study, the emotions that get the most clicks were joy and funny content,
second, controversy, third, anger, fourth, fear, and then nostalgia, curiosity, relatable, sad, and desire.
Desire is way down there. And this is a well-known marketing principle that most people will avoid pain
and they will pursue pleasure.
And so we have this desire and this thing we want to achieve.
Of course, we click on that.
But more often, we're going to click on, oh, pain could be coming or change is coming.
So that's super interesting.
In fact, you know, you talk about fear.
One of the videos that popped off for us, 25X outlier, was why YouTubers are getting sued,
fear and controversy.
The biggest legal mistakes creators make also fear, am I making those legal mistakes?
And again,
what is the six words? One, two, three, four, five, six words. So a lot of best practices
proving true. And then, of course, the strength of the topic itself. So the answer to this one is,
what are the top emotions that get the most views is humor, anger, and controversy? It doesn't mean
that's the only content you should create, but it does mean that you should create some of that content.
And your title's job is not to explain everything. It's to,
make people feel something. Number 11, are negative titles better than positive ones?
We just touched on that, but check it out. In education on the left, positive titles did the worst.
Neutral did the next best, and then negative did the best in educational content. And entertainment
was the same thing. Positive entertainment titles did the worst. Neutral did better. And negative
did a little bit better. And so ultimately, negativity.
in titles generally performs better, and whether that's educational or entertainment content.
And you might go, you know, I don't just, I don't want to go into the doom and gloom or I don't want
to be that type of creator. Well, great, that's totally fine. But it might be a tool in your tool belt
that you want to use sometimes. And there might be a way to package things where you can still be aligned
with your ethics, your values, and like the kind of content you want to make. Or like also what we'd
call ethically click-click baiting. You know, clickbait incit incinuates deception.
But if you're ethically clickbaiting, you're ultimately skilled at getting people to click on your content,
but delivering in the video in such a way where it's all authentic and not deceptive in any way.
And so I thought about this.
You know, the think media team packaged a really good video about the Roadcaster VideoS.
And, you know, creating a little bit of drama did Road just destroyed the Atem?
Of course, that's one of the best switchers.
Historically, RoadDropics.
a new product. So the positioning of the video kind of came into, you know, somewhat of a negative
or a dramatic approach. And that's a great way to package something. And maybe 99% of tech
creators wouldn't do it that way. Hence, you know, we continue to have high performing videos here at
think media. Answer, should you have negative titles or do negative titles perform better than
positive ones? Yes, they most of the time perform better. Because,
negative titles create tension. They trigger curiosity and they feel more urgent.
Neutral is safe. Negative is clickable. Now, in just a second, the big takeaway here is the question of,
how do I apply this to my own channel? And how do I apply all these things, whether I'm in entertainment
or education? I've got four things we all need to know. I'm going to share that in just a second.
But let's hit number 12 based on this report. What niches blow up easiest right now?
Ooh, it's a juicy question. What are the best chance?
channel topics. If you want to blow up easiest, there's actually a formula for this, I'll share in a
second, but here is what they shared in this report. You want to be in the upper right towards the
top. So median views is on the left. That's the Y axis. And the outlier score is on the X out
axis. So what are the, if you're going to have breakout videos consistently, you want the best of both worlds.
And so in the top right, what you're going to do? And so in the top right, what you're going to do you know,
see is movies and TV. You see music. You see sports up there. And then you also see
other. Well, what does other mean? Well, other includes animals, politics, history. Now, there's a really
strong insight we're going to learn in just a second. But what these combine is strong baseline demand,
frequent external trends, and a high outlier potential. A lot of fancy words. So you want a lot of baseline
people are interested in this. Frequent trends. If I was taking notes, that's what I would write down.
Does my niche have frequent trends? And is there a high outlier potential in my niche? The best ones
combine these things. So trends manufacture breakout videos, massive insight. So if your niche has
frequent trends, you have the opportunity to have frequent breakout videos. For example, in business and
that wasn't one of the hottest blow-up niches. And I'll know a lot of people that subscribe to us
are in that niche. They have lower medium views, lower outliers, if you're in business and finance.
And that doesn't mean it's a bad thing. It just means that, you know, finance is way down in the lower left
there. Business is on the right side a little bit further along. And it just means that it's harder.
So it's like, depending on the channel topic you select, breaking out consistently might be a little bit
what is the best niche to start? Well, let's summarize it into a formula. You want a big
audience and constant trends. You want a big audience. There's a marketing term, a business term,
called Tam, and it stands for the total addressable market, which speaks to the size of the market.
How big is the potential audience? And then the second piece of the framework or this formula is,
is there consistent trends happening? Is there constant trends happening in that topic? Because if there is,
constantly have things to talk about and new things to talk about. And then there's a big
enough audience that even if competition is fierce, there's a big audience for it. And so in the report,
they talked about movies and TV, music, politics, animals, history. And yes, trends happen in business
and finance, but you always got to know that even people that are pursuing building a business or, you know,
personal development and stuff, is always way smaller than people that are looking for movie content or
history content or animal content, you know. What are the coolest,
snakes on a plane. You know what I mean? And so one of the big insights here is virality isn't
actually random. Like, it really can be architected. And so this report reveals insight is step one. And I
got four ways to apply this for you personally. But inside is step one, like knowing these 12 things,
but execution is step two. Knowing is not enough. Most people fail because they actually fail to apply
this information to their channel. And this includes things like delivery. Can you talk on camera,
structure, consistency. So by the way, if you're committed to doing YouTube this year,
we have an event coming up. It's three days. It's free. It's going to be amazing. It's called
the YouTube Growth Sprint. It's all about helping you get results fast. There's a link in the
description if you want to register.Ytsprint.com. Three days of live training of a community.
And we're not just talking about what works. We're talking about how to apply it. It's a kick in the
pants. It's lighting a fire under your butt. We're going to go deep on making videos. People
actually want to watch. How do you actually start?
your content so that your retention doesn't fall apart. How about speaking on camera?
How about making videos in the first place? And how do you actually build momentum instead of just
posting random content? So this is going to be a lot of fun. And by the way, we do a ton of
giveaways. We give away software, cameras, light kits, microphones, all that kind of stuff.
So you can register for free. YTSprint.com. You know, it's our biggest event of the year. We always do
that stuff in January. Highly recommend you register, attend. It's going to be
fun and ytsprint.com is where you can get registered for that. If YouTube matters to you
matters to you this year, don't sit on the sidelines, get registered is completely free.
Now, I talked about four things. Here's what the right YouTube strategy depends on.
Number one, your niche. So education or entertainment, that's number two, intent,
education or entertainment. So what's the right YouTube strategy for you?
concept, you know, simple story driven thumbnail. For educational creators who are sitting
down and teaching someone to code, you could be getting millions of views or ranking videos
in an entirely different way. You know, you might want to do an AI tutorial that's like how to
master chat GPT in 2026, GBT's projects. You might want to even still tap into searchable aspects
of YouTube. So it depends. So what niche are you in? What's the intent of your audience? Are you in
of the day. Do you have an education channel or an entertainment channel? Let me know.
Also your channel size. And then also the viewer expectation. Very underrated insight.
What is the viewer expectation? Meaning how well do you understand your audience? And here's some homework.
People hate homework, but I'll give you it anyways. Have you studied your niche? So remember,
we want to look and see that the median amount of views that different topics get varies depending on
topic. So if you're out here thinking, you know, you're making 22 minute videos or an hour
hour and a half videos, does your niche support that? What are the best practices and video lengths
and title formats of outliers in your niche? These are really good questions to ask. So the right
YouTube strategy depends really on dialing in it personally for you. It's one of the things we'll be
doing on the YouTube sprint. And this report reviewed a few other, a few other deeper things.
and definitely diving the report more. It's a full like 100 page thing. And so there's a few
other insights that I saved for the end. And one of the kind of interesting things that the whole
report reveals is that creators are optimizing for what's easy to control, not what actually
matters. Here's what I mean. Most people's videos on YouTube overall are four to 10 minutes across
the platform. But peak performance is closer to 18 to 24 minutes. So it's like,
Like the majority is still just doing what everybody's doing, but the data shows like four to 10 minutes.
Again, you can break the rules, but like 18 to 24 is better.
Like, are you making data-driven decisions? When now you have this video and this report.
84% of thumbnails include text. 84% of thumbnails include text.
But text reduces views by 19%.
So creators are optimizing for what's easy to control or what everybody's doing instead of what actually works.
Titles average 10 words across YouTube.
performance drops sharply if you go longer than six words, exception for educational content.
So really, this reveals like creators copy norms. They don't copy what works. It's smarter to do what works.
And then one big takeaway is lower cognitive load wins everywhere. Let's define what that means
The shorter it is, the easy, every word adds more cognitive load makes your brain work harder.
So all of us, education or entertainment, should ask, how can we simplify our concepts and make the viewer work less to be able to click on this video.
So creating a lower cognitive load wins across niches.
That's your title length. It's your title character count.
Reading ease scores, like how easy it is to read text in your thumb,
thumbnail text size and even fewer characters in thumbnails. If you're going to use
titles, bottom line, it's like simple packaging, okay? Simple packaging. And you are responsible for
your own content. If you oversimplify too far, you might lose clarity. So it's like this process that
we have as entrepreneurs and creators to refine our concepts down to make them as simple as possible
just to reduce cognitive load because lower cognitive load wins everywhere.
To summarize, make it longer the people expected, long videos are crushing YouTube,
make it simpler than you think and make it easier to click on than everything else around it.
And by the way, we've been covering how to get views, but now let's talk about how to make money.
I actually did a video on how small channels are making $50 per day.
It's already a 7.8x outlier. People love this video. You can click or tap the screen to watch it.
profitable YouTube channel. Hit the like button and I can't wait to connect with you in a