came out like you know how much money only fans makes you're right if someone came out with
uh an erotica app where you could program it in it could be you your face and your favorite
actresses face and and that's the porn you watch they do it's all but is that that can't be
no it's china but you can you can actually be like i want connia west i want huge tits on conia
i don't want any you know big butt that's nuts
Yeah, I almost subscribed so many times.
Kanye with a BBL and big fat titties.
I mean, that would be awesome.
And he could fly away and become an eagle.
Yeah, you know, he can make it anything.
He finishes me off and he flies away.
And he winks at you.
And when he winks, he makes that Liberace noise.
Dink.
You remember that song when Liberacee winks at me?